Louis J. Budd Papers and compilation of Mark Twain Resources, 1980-2008, undated
Elmira College
- SERIES 3: MARK TWAIN INTERVIEWS, undated; This series compiled by Louis J. Budd contains photocopies and transcriptions of Mark Twain interviews. Dates reflect the date of the original article and not the date of reproduction. This series contains Budd’s original folder headings and is arranged ch
  - Chicago Inter-Ocean -- "Colony of Mermaids/Mark Twain to Exhibit a lot of Fish-Tailed Girls" -- "Not much quotation; Clemens was trying to get unnoticed by the press; registered as from East Chicago; explains that he has gathered some mermaids during his ocean voyages and will exhibit them in Chicago; item interesting only in showing how the press joked with Mark Twain through Orion writing to Mollie Clemens on 15 April 1893 (From Chicago) called it an interview", April 15, 1893
  - Illustrated Buffalo Express, Saint Louis Republic -- "Mark Twain and the Reporter/Mark Twain Came Abroad" -- "Clemens in garrulous and joking mood; mentions his working habits, tells the glass-eye story, discusses his after-dinner speaking" (With Notes, April 1, 1894
  - Paris Figaro -- "Gabriel Random, Mark Twain" -- Much background commentary; Clemens names his favorite authors, and especially his French favorites; he tells an anecdote contrasting French and American character", April 5, 1894
  - New York SUN -- "Mark Twain is Back in Town/Has Been Abroad to See His Wife, Who Was Ill in Paris" -- "Brief; Clemens discusses his wife's health and sea voyage", April 15, 1894
  - New York SUN -- "Mark Twain Goes Abroad" -- "Clemens jokes about whether he is on passenger list; briefly discusses his wife's health and European doctors", August 16, 1894
  - New York Sun -- "Mark Twain in Paris" -- "Clemens on French character and culture, especially French reputation for wit", January 27, 1895
  - Cleveland Plain Dealer -- "Mark Twain/His Scheme for Regeneration of Human Race/He Makes a Startling Confession/He Says That in His Plan of Regeneration He Has Passed Through Two-Thirds of the Crimes of Which the Human Race is Capable", July 16, 1895
  - Cleveland, Sydney Australian Star -- "A Trip Around the World" -- "Clemens on duel in Nevada and SF CALL days" (With Correspondence), July 16, 1895
  - Petoskey Restorer -- "Mark Twain on Yachting/Something Concerning the Great Humorist" -- "Clemens much prefers yachting on the lakes rather than the ocean" -- "Clemens discusses how he borrowed his pen name, evades question of authorship of 'Joan' book, reacts to a local newspaper", July 21, 1895
  - "Next Stop Detroit: A City's Views of Mark Twain's Evolution as a Literary Hero 1868-1895, July 18, 1895
  - Minneapolis Journal -- "Not Roughing it Now/Mark Twain Reaches Minneapolis on His 'World Belting' Trip/He Tells of His Recent Life" -- "Clemens comments on his wife and Howells as editors of his work", July 23, 1895
  - Minneapolis Penny Press -- "Mark Twain/The Celebrated Humorist Arrives in the City Today" -- "Discusses his wife and daughters as editors, praises Kipling, and generalizes about what kind of humor will endure", July 23, 1895
  - Minneapolis Times -- "In Private Life" -- "No direct quotations; Clemens praises Kipling, Bill Nye, and James Whitcomb Riley, and names 'Huckleberry Finn' as his favorite among his own books", July 24, 1895
  - Manitoba Evening Free Press -- "A Chat with Clemens/Mark Twain Talks About Himself, His Books, and His Aggravating Carbuncle" -- "Clemens prefers Huckleberry Finn over Tom Sawyer and squelches Max O'Rell; routine, almost brief", July 27, 1895
  - Winnipeg (Canada) Nor-Western -- "An Interview with Mark Twain" -- "Clemens praises Hartford, Conn., calls for better copyright laws, reminisces about Artemus Ward, and recalls some tributes in Germany", July 27, 1895
  - Winnipeg (Canada) Tribune -- "Mark Twain's Lecture" -- "Clemens comments on lecturing and on his feeling that river life on the Mississippi was his 'field of work'", July 27, 1895
  - Grand Forks (N. Dakota) Herald -- "Mark Twain Talks" -- "Not important; somewhat brief; Clemens comments on the way the grass prairies look like a mighty ocean; asks many questions, reportedly, about Grand Forks", July 30, 1895
  - Helena (Montana) Herald -- "Mark Twain is Here/The Eminent Humorist, Author and Lecturer on His First Trip to Montana's Capital" -- "Quoted passages reproduce (without credit) material from Minneapolis Journal July 23, 1895", August 3, 1895
  - Tacoma (Wash) Morning Union -- "He Lost His Trunk Keys/Mark Twain is Seriously Embarrassed for Clean Clothes" -- "Paraphrase of superficial remarks about scenery", August 9, 1895
  - Toronto Globe -- "Mark Twain Interviewed" -- "Not consequential though it shows Mark Twain quiet, informal mood before he rises into mock-oration over a broken bottle of whiskey", August 10, 1895
  - Portland Sunday Oregonian -- "Mark Twain Talks/The Famous Story-Teller Discusses Characters/Says That No Author Creates, but Merely Copies--How to Write a Guide Book" -- "Clemens also discusses monopolies and travel books (Clemens praised this interview)", August 11, 1895
  - Seattle Post-Intelligence -- "The Same Old Twain" -- "Clemens praises the vistas of scenery and discusses tricks played by visual perspective; long anecdote about choosing his pen name; details on first publication of jumping frog story", August 11, 1895
  - Tacoma (Washington) Morning Union -- "Mark Twain and Major Pond/They Talk about Each Other and Discusses Everything save Humorists" -- "Much space devoted to Pond as Clemens keeps drifting in and out of the interview; he says most about palmistry", August 11, 1895
  - Seattle Post-Intelligence -- "Mark Twain Brands a Fake/But It Does Not Irritate Him--Talk of Cable and Lecturing" --"Clemens repudiates a faked interview about mortuary poetry; denies that Cable and he broke up their lecture tour in a quarrel", August 14, 1895
  - San Francisco Examiner -- "Mark Twain to Pay All", August 17, 1895
  - New Whatcom Blade -- "Mark Twain Seriously Embarrassed for Clean Clothes/Mark Twain Unsuited" -- "Brief comment on poor visibility in area because of smoke", August 17, 1895
  - New York Times, New York Tribune -- "Mark Twain Plan of Settlement/Why Mark Twain Lectures" -- "A detailed, prepared statement", August 17, 1895
  - Vancouver (B. C.) Daily News Advertiser -- "Mark Twain Talks/About Lecturing and Lectures--Pleasant Half Hour in the Company of the Great Humorist" -- "Long comment on attitudes and psychology of audiences; diatribe against hotel keepers who are stingy about lighting", August 20, 1895
  - San Francisco Examiner -- "Twain's Programme" -- "Greater detail on his bankruptcy and his plans for paying the debt; Clemens speaks warmly of his reception so far and exudes cheerfulness (perhaps Clemens wrote the text, August 24, 1895
  - Vancouver or Victoria (B.C.) -- "Mark Twain Very Ill/Ruined at 60, He Starts 'round the World/But Talks in His Usual Vein Before He Goes/Where His Head Where His Feet Ought to Be, Twain Tells a Good Story on Saint Louis--Discusses Hotel Lights, Bell Boys and National Politics Until His Agent Makes Him Stop the Conversation" -- "Highly similar to item in Vancouver Daily New-Advertiser, 20 August 1895" (With Correspondence), August 24, 1895
  - The Australian Star - Saturday Evening "Very Much Abroad Mr. Clemens on Tour A Trip Around the World", September 14, 1895
  - Melbourne (Australia) Argus -- "Mark Twain at Sydney" -- "Clemens briefly discusses his literary quarrel with Max O'Rell", September 16, 1895
  - Sydney (Australia) Daily Telegraph -- "A Ramble with Mark Twain/His View on Men and Things" -- "Clemens defends free trade and Henry George's ideas on ownership of land; tells story of plagiarizing from Oliver Wendell Holmes; comments on Scotts and his style; declares he is humorous rather than witty", September 17, 1895
  - Sydney (Australia) Morning Herald -- "Visit of Mark Twain/Wit and Humor" -- "Long discussion of humor and its relation to pathos and wit; judgments of W.S. Gilbert, Dickens, Pope, Ulysses Grant, Kipling, Harte' Clemens explains need for "third party" in politics", September 17, 1895
  - Melbourne (Australia) Argus -- "Mark Twain at Sydney" -- "Comments on seriousness of life, his reputed laziness, Ulysses Grant, Bret Harte, Kipling, and Hawthorne", September 16, 1895
  - Sydney Australian Star -- "An Interview with Mark Twain" (With Correspondence), September 21, 1895
  - Sydney (Sunday) Truth -- "Our American Cousin" -- "A very playful item; hard to tell whether it is authentic; Clemens explains of having been hounded by reporters", September 22, 1895
  - Sydney (Australia) Sunday Times -- "A Chat with Mark Twain/Impressions of Public Men/Australian and American Audiences/Criticism of Bret Harte--What He Thinks of Interviewing--Lecturing v Authorship--His Favorite Work" -- "Long item; mostly direct quotation", September 22, 1895
  - Sydney Truth (Australia) -- "Mark Twain" -- "Long but unimportant because highly fanciful and quite possibly a total fabrication", September 22, 1895
  - Melbourne Evening News -- "Mark Twain in the Sydney Express" -- "Clemens, in a general mood, diplomatically praises the landscape and the Australian writer Marcus Clarke; briefly comments on Dickens and on 'Prince and Pauper'", September 26, 1895
  - Melbourne Herald -- "The Tramp in Melbourne/A Morning with Mark Twain/Jokes and Jottings" -- Clemens chats genially, praises Marcus Clarke's Novel", September 26, 1895 - September 27, 1895
  - Melbourne (Australia) Age -- "Mark Twain/Arrival in Melbourne" -- "Clemens praises both progress and preserving some relics of past; suggests that purely humorous books do not last; describes his writing habits; decries hasty judgments by travelers", September 27, 1895
  - Melbourne (Australia) Age -- "Mark Twain/Arrival in Melbourne" -- "Clemens praises both progress and preserving some relics of past; suggests that purely humorous books do not last; describes his writing habits; decries hasty judgments by travelers", October 14, 1895
  - South Australian Register -- "Mark Twain Put to the Question" -- "Clemens discusses interviews, Kipling poetry, false notions about Americans and Southern violence, racial minorities, the "Jumping Frog" story", October 14, 1895
  - Licensing (?) Guardian (New South Wales) -- "Mark Twain on Prohibition", September, 1895 - December, 1895
  - Balart Courier -- "A Chat with Mark Twain: Impression of Australia" -- "No direct quotation; Mark Twain diplomatic; main Australian cities, scenery, (?), and character which is highly similar of American character, especially in frankness", October 21, 1895
  - Hobart (Australia) Tasmanian News -- "Mark Twain/Arrival in Hobart" -- "Probably in most part a pastiche of earlier interviews, especially that in Sydney Herald, 17 September 1895", November 2, 1895
  - Hobart (Tasmania) Mercury -- "Mark Twain in Hobart/Save Impressions and a Interview" -- "Diplomatic remarks about Australian people and scenery", November 4, 1895
  - Dandier (New Zealand) Otego Daily Times -- "M. Ross: A Chat with Mark Twain" -- "Long item with few quotations; Clemens discusses habit of working intermittently on a manuscript", November 6, 1895
  - Christchurch (New Zealand) Press -- "Mark Twain Home/A Chat with Mr. Clemens" -- "Clemens declines to make quick judgments on Australia and New Zealand, praises the scenery, compares American and "colonial audiences, praises Zew Zealand journalism", November 13, 1895
  - Christchurch (New Zealand) Canterbury Times/The Lyttelton Times -- "Mark Twain/A Talk with the Famous Humorist" -- "Brief reference to many subjects: Knights of Labor, habit of laying manuscripts aside for a while, superficial travel books, and lecture audiences", November 13, 1895
  - Auekland New Zealand Herald -- "Mark Twain/Arrival in Auekland" -- "Prolonged discussion of American versus British humor and of Americanisms in speech", November 21, 1895
  - Wellington New Zealand Mail -- "A Chat with Mark Twain" -- "Clemens reminisces about Territorial Enterprise, Civil War (Service), publication of Jumping Frog story, the Holy Land trip, the Prince and the Pauper, and writing his own obituary", December 12, 1895
  - Sydney (Australia) Daily Telegraph -- "Mark Twain/His Tour Through New Zealand" -- Clemens refuses to give impressions of Zew Zealand since he went through so little of it so hurriedly; criticizes, briefly, hasty travelers who express opinions on the United States", December 20, 1895
  - Overland Times of Ceylon, Ceylon Observer -- "Mark Twain in Colombo, January 14, 1896
  - Sydney (N. S. W.) Bulletin -- "Interview with Mark Twain" -- "Solid item; Clemens discusses his books, tastes in reading, writing habits, and dreams", January 4, 1896
  - Ceylon Independent -- "Mark Twain in Ceylon/He Will Return to Lecture" -- "Summary of an extended, casual talk with Clemens, who compares public buildings in Ceylon and U.S.", January 15, 1896
  - Bombay Gazette -- "Mark Twain on His Methods of Work" -- "Detailed comments on when he works, how long, where, and how much he turns out; also comments lengthily on how much he prepares for his readings", January 23, 1896
  - Bombay Times of India -- "Interview with Mark Twain" -- "Clemens sums up his journalistic career from Virginia City to Innocents Abroad; discusses Kipling, his new working habits, and interviewing", January 23, 1896
  - Bombay India Gazette -- Mark Twain Relations Between England and America/Americans Not Unfriendly" -- "Clemens praises vigor and modernity of English-speaking peoples; strongly decries and idea of war over Venezuela question; insists that majority of Americans do not share anti-British feelings of their newspapers; defends British copyright law", January 24, 1896
  - The Asian (Calcutta) -- "Interview with Mark Twain" -- "Clemens discusses scenery, gives anecdotes about his faux pas at a diner party and a clerk who failed to recognize his pen name", February 7, 1896
  - Calcutta Englishmen -- "Mark Twain Interviewed/First Impressions of India" -- "Comments on Indian scenery, visit to a holy recluse, caste system. British rule of India, treatment of red Indians in Canada and United States, and the Negro question in United States", February 8, 1896
  - Calcutta Statesman -- "Mark Twain in Calcutta" -- Clemens gives impressions of Indian scenery and railways", February 8, 1896
  - Calcutta Indian Daily News -- "Mark Twain in Calcutta" -- "Clemens comments on value of copyright of his books", March 26, 1896
  - Reis and Ragget (Calcutta) -- "Mark Twain in Madras/An Interview in the Harbor--His Opinion on Mr. Skrine's book An Indian Journalist" -- "Detailed comments on publishing contracts, poverty in India, and England and United States as sources of inventions", April 11, 1896
  - Durban (S.A.) Natal Mercury -- "Mark Twain in Durban/A Bedside Chat with the Humorist" -- "Clemens says much on Venezuela crisis, copyright, current (?), and Portugal as imperial power", May 8, 1896
  - Johannesburg Standard and Deggers' News -- "Mark Twain: The Humorist at Home/How He Tackled a New York Irishman/A Mark Twain Yarn" -- "Table talk rather than interview; most space given to Clemens's anecdote of how he got past Daly's Irish doorkeeper; he jokingly mentions the criticism of Standard Oil Co., praises the sunsets in Florence, Italy, and comments on the local locust plague", May 18, 1896
  - Johannesburg (S.A.) Star -- "A Chat with Mark Twain/English and Americans/Some Authors He Knows/The Sense of Humor" -- "On the British-American relations, current Presidential election in United States, his books, W.D. Howells, and Edward Bellamy", May 18, 1896
  - Johannesburg (S.A.) Times -- "Mark Twain on the Rand/He Gives a Few Opinions/A Chat with the Humorist" -- "Clemens comments on complexity of current politics in Union of South Africa and on his curiosity about Cecil Rhodes; discusses Story of an American Farm", May 18, 1896
  - Pretoria (South Africa) Press -- "A Chat at the Hotel" -- "Few quotations; summary of Clemens Jameson Raiders and Johannesburg", May 25, 1896
  - Kimberley (S.A.) Deamond Fields Advertiser -- "Mark Twain at Queenstown" -- "Brief, but Clemens comments on problems of having a reputation as a humorous writer", June 10, 1896
  - Eastern Province Herald (S.A.) -- "Mark Twain/In Port Elizabeth" -- "On Jameson Raiders, railway travel, Venezuela crisis with stress on Anglo-American rapprochement", June 19, 1896
  - London African Critic -- "Stage and Sport/The Sketch/Critique and Causerie" -- "Clemens on Shriner, copyright, and pernicious French novels repeated from interviews in NATAL WITNESS, 8 May, and Johannesburg TIMES, 18 May, with F.L. Austin's criticism in London SKETCH", June 20, 1896
  - Midland News and Karroo Farmer (S.A.) -- "Mark Twain", June 30, 1896
  - New York Journal -- "Mark Twain Amused/Humorist Says He Even Heard on Good Authority that He was Dead/Cousin, Not, Sick/New Book Just Finished, and It Will Be Called 'Another Innocent Abroad'" -- "One long quotation, which includes the famous, "The report of my death is an exaggeration", June 2, 1897
  - New York Herald -- "Mark Twain Smiling Through His Tears, but in Sore Straits/Celebrated American Humorist Tells of His Affairs, and the Herald Starts a Subscription for Him" -- "Clemens discusses his health and his forthcoming travel book, criticizes French courts and severe punishments, tell anecdote about donating to charity", June 13, 1897
  - Springfield Sunday Republican -- "A Recent Interview with Mark Twain" -- "Two long paragraphs quote the account of a London correspondent of a New York paper; differs in interesting details from interview in New York Herald (item 132)", July 25, 1897
  - Review of Reviews -- "Mark Twain Character Sketch", August, 1897
  - Vienna News Freie Press -- "Ein Besuch Fei Mark Twain" -- "Clemens expresses his interest in Austria, declares he will be slow to make judgments about it, and discusses the naming of his book of travel", October 1, 1897
  - Russian Interview with Mark Twain -- Odesski Novosti, October 9, 1897
  - New York World -- "Mark Twain in Vienna" -- "Basically a story on Clemens personal popularity in Vienna, a quoted comment on the uproar in the Reichsrath", December 13, 1897
  - Illustrated Zeitung -- "Mark Twain" -- " J.B.C. Kinch calls this an interview; but her precis makes this sound like an article and my own rough-reading indicates a non-interview", December 23, 1897
  - New York World -- "Mark Twain Proud and Happy/That's the way it Feels, He Says, to Be out of Debt--Longing for Home" -- "Brief; Clemens insists he is not a bad businessman", March 13, 1898
  - (Budapest) Magyar Hirlap -- "S.H. in Budapest", March 24, 1899
  - Budapest Pesti Naplo -- "With Mark Twain from Galatia to Budapest" (With Negatives, March 24, 1899
  - London Times -- "Mark Twain Bequest" -- "Clemens discusses his work on a book of portraits of persons he has known: candid and not primarily humorous, it will not be published for a hundred years", May 23, 1899
  - Visit with Emperor, May 25, 1899
  - Mark Twain and Vienna -- "Farewell", May 26, 1899 - May 27, 1899
  - London Chronicle -- "Mark Twain in London/He Talks of His Visit and His Doomsday Book/Vienna and the Emperor/The Tragedy of the Speech Done in German/Anglo-American Union" -- "Clemens discusses the collected edition of his his writings, in preparation, and his current writing (the autobiography, perhaps); ends with friendly comments on British-American solidarity, June 3, 1899
  - Stenholm Aftonbladet -- "Mark Twain" -- "Clemens at Sana; Clemens jokes about the climate, Cook's mismanagement of his baggage, his excellent health, his indefinite literary plans, the curious abundance of American flies in Sweden, and Anglo-American friendship as the bulwark against Russian expansionism", July 13, 1899
  - Buffalo Express -- "Mark Twain Talks: That Book for Year 1999" -- "Long, solid item; Clemens says much about his book of portraits of contemporaries that he will withhold from publication in his lifetime", July 30, 1899
  - New York World -- "Mark Twain Says He's Discouraged/Every Sort of Crank except Himself Has a Presidential Following/Is Advised to Withdraw But He Thinks it Unnecessary..." -- "Clemens jokes about running for the presidency; declares that when he returns home, he will stay", June 17, 1900
  - New York Herald -- "Mark Twain Returns After Nine Years" -- "Clemens berates the beds in British hotels but makes firm statement for Anglo-American unity", October 4, 1900
  - New York World -- "Twain on the Sea, Glad to Start Home/At Work on Reminiscences to Be Published One Hundred Years After He Dies, He Writes Freely/Imperialism Stumps Him/Doesn't Understand How it is That We Are Fighting the Filipinos, Whom We Were to Set Free, He Supposed" -- "Essentially a shorter version of interview in New York World of 14 October 1900", October 7, 1900
  - New York World -- "Mark Twain, the Greatest American Humorist, Returning Home, Talks at Length to the World/He Likes to Dine Out/For That Reason London Has Proved a Delightful Place of Residence/We've No Business in China/Nor Can He Understand on Just what Principles We Are Proceeding in the Philippines" -- "Clemens comments on Holy Land trip and on working for San Francisco Call", October 14, 1900
  - Chicago Tribune -- "Mark Twain in America Again/Humorist Home After His Nine Years of Wandering in Distant Lands/Talks of the Future/Although an Anti-Imperialist He Says He Prefers McKinley to W.J. Bryan/Important Work Ahead" -- "One of the more compact interviews on this occasion", October 16, 1900
  - New York Evening Seen -- "Mark Twain Home Again/Hale and Happy at 65--His Book of 100 Years After" -- "Touches on several subjects, none in more detail than in other interviews of same date", October 16, 1900
  - New York Herald and Evening Telegram -- "Mark Twain Home, An Anti-Imperialist/Views of the Author Changed During His Long Travels in Foreign Elands, but He Will Not Support Bryan/Notes of the Author's Trip Around the Globe" -- "Very long item; Clemens comments on his reputation for truth, world and domestic politics, experiences during his world tour, and plans for writing", October 16, 1900
  - New York Press -- "Mark Twain Wants to be President/Humorist Arrives Home After Nine Years Abroad" -- "Stress on political opinions", October 16, 1900
  - New York SUN -- "Mark Twain Home Again/He Went Away with a Load of Debt Which He Voluntarily Assumed, and Has Paid It all Off--He Will Not Lecture Again, He Says, Unless He Is Compelled To" -- "Clemens announces his anti-imperialism, discusses paying off his creditors", October 16, 1900
  - New York Tribune -- "Mark Twain Home/Arrives in Minnehaha with Wife and Daughters" -- "One of better versions, both for substance and coherence; Clemens discusses current politics, his literary plans, and his immediate future, and reviews his travels since 1891", October 16, 1900
  - New York World -- "Mark Twain Home Again Hale and Happy at 65/After Nine Years Abroad, He Declares That He Will Break Both Legs, So That He Cannot Leave America Again--To Winter in New York" -- "Shorter, much less political than other interviews", October 16, 1900
  - New York Mail and Express -- "Mark Twain Talks/Says His Chief Desire Is Not to Be Told to Move On" -- "Clemens says most about being a mugwump", October 16, 1900
  - New York Times -- "Mark Twain Home Again/Talks Freely of His Travels, His Experiences, and His Triumphs--In the Best of Health" -- "Clemens has much to say on politics and gives details of his visit to Jameson Raiders", October 16, 1900